<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.4.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="likeafuckinggrownup.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="likeafuckinggrownup.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-10-14T15:45:16+02:00</updated><id>likeafuckinggrownup.com/</id><title type="html">Like a Fucking Grownup</title><subtitle>Live the life you really want to live, by learning Adulting superpowers.
</subtitle><author><name>Sam Beckbessinger</name><email>howzit@fuckinggrownups.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">Five things you didn’t learn about STIs in Sex-Ed</title><link href="likeafuckinggrownup.com/etc/stis.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Five things you didn't learn about STIs in Sex-Ed" /><published>2019-09-26T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-09-26T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>likeafuckinggrownup.com/etc/stis</id><content type="html" xml:base="likeafuckinggrownup.com/etc/stis.html">&lt;p&gt;But, despite the national preoccupation with sexually transmitted infections (STIs), most of us – adult humans who might have sex sometimes – are still walking around with some pretty outrageous misconceptions about them. For the first episode of our podcast, I talked to some sexual health experts and discovered there was a bunch of stuff about sexual health I WAS GROSSLY MISINFORMED ABOUT.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/tortoises.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Tortoises smooshing squishy bits&quot; title=&quot;Tortoises smooshing squishy bits&quot; style=&quot;max-width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read the rest of this article and take a listen to the first episode of &lt;em&gt;Like a Fucking Grownup: the PODCAST!&lt;/em&gt; over on &lt;em&gt;Daily Maverick&lt;/em&gt;: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dailymaverick.co.za/article/2019-09-26-five-things-you-didnt-learn-about-stis-in-sex-ed/&quot;&gt;Five Things You Didn’t Learn About STIs in Sex-Ed&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Sam Beckbessinger</name><email>howzit@fuckinggrownups.com</email></author><category term="sex" /><category term="health" /><category term="podcast" /><summary type="html">But, despite the national preoccupation with sexually transmitted infections (STIs), most of us – adult humans who might have sex sometimes – are still walking around with some pretty outrageous misconceptions about them. For the first episode of our podcast, I talked to some sexual health experts and discovered there was a bunch of stuff about sexual health I WAS GROSSLY MISINFORMED ABOUT.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Raising money-savvy kids 👧🏽</title><link href="likeafuckinggrownup.com/etc/raising-money-savvy-kids.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Raising money-savvy kids 👧🏽" /><published>2019-09-19T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-09-19T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>likeafuckinggrownup.com/etc/raising-money-savvy-kids</id><content type="html" xml:base="likeafuckinggrownup.com/etc/raising-money-savvy-kids.html">&lt;p&gt;Last week someone asked me for advice about how to talk to her kid about money. “It’s not like I can just show her what’s in my bank account”, she said, laughing nervously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I told her, actually, that’s exactly what I think she should do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/youngsam.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Young Sam&quot; title=&quot;Young Sam&quot; style=&quot;max-width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Your author: an extremely dorky kid with some weird ideas about how the world works.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We never spoke about money when I was growing up. In my house you could make jokes about sex at the dinner table, you could have a robust and respectful discussion about politics or religion, but I do not remember a single conversation we ever had as a family about how money works, or our family’s financial situation. Ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Money was the final taboo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the thing is, when you’re not talking to your kids about something, that doesn’t mean they’re not still developing an alarmingly sophisticated understanding of what’s going on. Kids are sponges sucking up information about the world. They hear the anxious fights you have through closed doors. They sense when you’re stressed about covering the bills this month. They’re learning some fundamental beliefs about money, beliefs that it might take them a lifetime to unlearn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a researcher named &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.yourmentalwealthadvisors.com/sites/default/files/users/nathanwalsh3/Studies/studytwo/Money%20beliefs%20and%20financial%20behaviors-%20Development%20of%20the%20Klontz%20Money%20Script%20Inventory-%20Journal%20of%20Financial%20Therapy%202011.pdf&quot;&gt;Brad Klontz&lt;/a&gt; who studies money beliefs and how they correlate with life outcomes. He groups the ideas we hold about money into four basic groups:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Money avoidance.&lt;/strong&gt; “Rich people are greedy.” “People get rich by taking advantage of others.” “It’s not okay to have more than you need.” “I don’t deserve a lot of money when other people have less than me.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Money worship.&lt;/strong&gt; “More money will make you happier.” “There will never be enough money.” “Money is power.” “Things would get better if I had more money.” “I will never be able to afford the things I really want in life.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Money status.&lt;/strong&gt; “Your self-worth equals your net-worth.” “I won’t buy something unless it’s new.” “If you live a good life, you’ll always have enough money.” “Most poor people don’t deserve to have money.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Money vigilance.&lt;/strong&gt; “It’s important to save for a rainy day.” “If you can’t pay cash for something, you shouldn’t buy it.” “Money should be saved, not spent.” “You shouldn’t tell people how much you have or make.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are other money stories I’ve encountered in my chats with people. “Climate change is going to throw us all into a Mad Max-style wasteland so the only sensible investment is potable water” has come up a few times. Also, “my retirement plan is to kill myself when I’m too old to work,” (geez, fellow 30-somethings, you’re a morbid bunch).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which of these money stories are true? All of them, probably, even the ones that contradict each other. All of them capture part of the truth. But none of them are the whole truth. And some of them are more helpful to you, at particular times in your life, than others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My mum, who grew up about as poor as it was possible for a white South African to be in the 60s, carries a lot of the “money worship” beliefs. I think many people who grow up poor end up with the words NOT ENOUGH MONEY banging around their brains like a jackhammer. It’s fear-motivated, this conviction that money will fix all your problems, so if you have problems, it’s because you don’t have enough money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thing is, this belief was definitely true during some parts of her life when she objectively did not have enough money. But it still felt true to her during times when she had plenty; times when the things that were wrong in her life had nothing to do with money at all. Even when she was pretty financially stable, my mum was constantly talking about what she was going to do when she won the lotto. She always had an acute sense of the things she can’t afford, the life she could be living but wasn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For my dad, money was about status, and it was how he demonstrated his love. If my dad had five rand left in his bank account, he would spend that last five rand buying you ice cream. Money moved through his life like water. If he had it, he’d spend it without thinking, and mostly, he’d spend it on other people. If you mentioned that you kinda half-liked a bizarre overpriced hat you saw in a store window, he would march out immediately and buy you that hat, whether you actually had any use for it or not. If he didn’t have the cash, he’d buy it on credit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Money was always like a happy surprise, to my dad. Like, “oh look, money! What a strange and remarkable thing to find in my bank account! Let’s go spend it, quick, before it vanishes as mysteriously as it arrived!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both of them were amazing parents who loved their kids. And both of their money philosophies kind of made sense. But also were kind of insane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can imagine how hilarious the interplay was between my parents. My mom would literally hide money from my dad. And thank god, too, because my mom was the only one thinking about how we were going to pay for less exciting magical goodies like school fees (and my dad’s significant credit card bills). But she’d also take us one side tearfully every single year and warn us that they couldn’t afford to buy us proper Christmas presents that year (which was nuts: we always had way over-the-top Christmas presents, but she never felt like it was enough, and was always convinced that we were on the brink of financial disaster). It was a confusing time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I, a dumb kid, thereby concluded two irrefutable facts about my family’s financial situation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We did not have enough money!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We had plenty of money!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And because my parents never actually had a conversation with me about any of this, I never had a chance to reflect on questions like what it would actually mean to have enough money, how does one go about getting money in the first place, and how to make decisions about how to spend the money you do have. In this information vacuum, I started forming some money beliefs of my own:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You have no control over how much money you have.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Money is mysterious and it’s impossible to know whether you have enough or not.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It’s weird and wrong to ever talk about money (I’m making up for this now by talking about money ALL THE TIME AT VERY INAPPROPRIATE MOMENTS).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It took me a long, long time to unpick these ideas from my brain, and replace them with more helpful beliefs that don’t leave me feeling so passive and bewildered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My dear, sweet parents who wanted nothing but the best for us, did all they could to protect us from difficult, adult money conversations. But the thing is, when you think you’re not teaching your kids about something, you might be accidentally teaching them the wrong things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, what if you tried being radically honest with your kids? What if you brought them into family financial decisions? What if you gave them the gift of better money scripts than the ones you grew up with?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why am I talking about any of this? Because I’m working on a book about money for teens (aged 11-14ish). And I need your help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My only qualifications for writing this book are that 1. I have been a teenager and 2. that I have the sense of humour of a 9 year old (it’s all fart jokes). I am missing one pretty important qualification: I don’t actually have kids. I don’t have a good grasp of what questions kids are asking about money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are they worried about what kinds of subjects to choose and how to think about jobs? Are they budgeting their pocket money? Do they still have lemonade stands and sell silkworms, or all they all trading Bitcoin now? Are they trying to invest the millions they’ve earned being Twitch streamers?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you know some kids, please tell me what questions they’re asking about money, so I can write them some profanity-free, joke-filled answers in an easy-to-read book. And if you’ve had conversations with your kids about money that went well, or if you’ve tried exercises with them that made a difference, I’d like to hear about those too, so that we can grow a generation of kids that are smarter and better-adjusted than we are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mega smooches, friends!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Love,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sam&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Sam Beckbessinger</name><email>howzit@fuckinggrownups.com</email></author><category term="investing" /><category term="money" /><category term="kids" /><category term="psychology" /><summary type="html">Last week someone asked me for advice about how to talk to her kid about money. “It’s not like I can just show her what’s in my bank account”, she said, laughing nervously. I told her, actually, that’s exactly what I think she should do.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What roller coasters can teach you about stress 🎢</title><link href="likeafuckinggrownup.com/etc/what-roller-coasters-can-teach-you-about-stress.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What roller coasters can teach you about stress 🎢" /><published>2019-08-14T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-08-14T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>likeafuckinggrownup.com/etc/what-roller-coasters-can-teach-you-about-stress</id><content type="html" xml:base="likeafuckinggrownup.com/etc/what-roller-coasters-can-teach-you-about-stress.html">&lt;p&gt;Three days after my dad died, two of my best friends took me to Gold Reef City to ride rollercoasters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/stress.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;The Golden Loop rollercoaster&quot; title=&quot;The Golden Loop rollercoaster&quot; style=&quot;max-width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ah, the Golden Loop, you magnificent fearbeast!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that seems like an extremely strange way for friends to help you process grief, but I tell you, it was probably the most helpful thing that they could have done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The year before my dad died felt like a slow-motion nightmare. The things that were happening were impossible and terrible. But there was also a lot of admin. A lot of decisions to be made. A lot of keeping it together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A long scream, held inside for months and months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you know what made me feel much better? Therapy? Journalling? Actually processing my feelings like a normal person?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nope!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What made me feel better was strapping myself into a metal tube and being thrown around loop-de-loops at high speeds. Screaming until I laughed. Screams that were like steam being let out from a pressure cooker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This all happened a long time ago, now, but it’s something I think about often. Because I think there’s a pretty profound lesson in there about how our brains work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I told my extremely wise and emotionally competent friend Charne about my amazing roller coaster discovery, she sent me some passages from a book by Emily Nagoski, which stuck with me:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stress underlies worry, anxiety, fear, terror, all the variants of “Run away!” But it also underlies anger - irritation, annoyance, frustration, rage. And to a great extent it underlies the shutdown that characterises depression… The key to managing stress… is not simply “relaxing” or “calming down.” It’s allowing the stress response cycle to complete. Allow it to discharge fully. Let your body move all the way from “I am at risk” to “I am safe.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, more simply:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Emotions are tunnels. You have to go all the way through the darkness to get to the light at the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thing is, human brains evolved to deal with dangers like being hunted down and eaten by lions. Falling off cliffs. Being stabbed by other humans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Human brains DID NOT evolve to handle things like wondering whether your boss hates you and might fire you, or feeling like you can’t choose what you want out of life, or worrying whether your partner might leave you, or figuring out how to juggle the forty-seven-million different responsibilities you have, or the ice caps melting, or wondering whether one of the maniacal strongmen presidents that run the world right now is going to start a nuclear war, or any of the other things that make being alive in 2019 so damned stressful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And yet our bodies still respond to stress the same way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/stress-tegan.png&quot; alt=&quot;Tegan Phillips on stress&quot; title=&quot;Tegan Phillips on stress&quot; style=&quot;max-width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As my lovely buddy &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.weeklyscribble.com/?offset=1562569200955&quot;&gt;Tegan Phillips&lt;/a&gt; described it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you’re being chased by a lion, stress hormones like adrenaline and cortisol put your body into a GO! GO! GO! state where you’re ready for ACTION! This activates your body so that you can WRESTLE that big dumb catto to DEFEAT or you can DEFEND your little buddies or you can SPRINT your ass the hell away from it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you’re trying to survive a lion attack, you either succeed and you survive, or you fail and you die.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if you survive, how do you feel? Amazing! Relieved! Grateful to be alive! That’s what it means to complete the stress response cycle. You did something with all those GO hormones. And afterwards, you’re flooded with endorphins and it feels freaking GREAT.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what happens if you don’t get to do anything with those stress hormones? What if the person making you feel unsafe you isn’t a lion, but your boss? Or the patriarchy? Or systemic inequality? There’s nowhere to run to and nothing to hit (attacking your boss is commonly frowned upon, in my experience).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s when your stress hormones switch into freeze mode. Your body starts yelling STOP instead of GO. You shut down like a rabbit about to be run over by a car. All those bad feelings stay inside of you and they rot. And even if the thing that caused the stress goes away, you can still feel awful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It took me a long time to learn this incredibly simple lesson: removing the stressor does not automatically remove the stress. Stress sits in your body, and you’ve got to exorcise it out. Or, exercise it out (snigger) 🏃🏾‍♀️.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of us understand that stress literally makes us sick. We carry our pain and our traumas in our bodies. But we don’t often talk about the fact that this works the other way around, too: you can hack your brain through physical experiences. You can force yourself to smile and you will actually feel happier. You can outrun imaginary lions and feel the swee, sweet rush of survival.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As much as we think that we need to figure out all of our problems with our GIANT SMART BRAINS, sometimes what we really need is to just feel something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, the best way to manage stress is just to complete the stress cycle. Unlock from freeze, escape the predator, rejoice. Simulate it if you have to. Watch a horror movie. Go for a run and &lt;a href=&quot;https://zombiesrungame.com/&quot;&gt;pretend that zombies are chasing you&lt;/a&gt;. Go to a boxing class. Try skydiving. Or sit with a friend and have a good cry and let yourself feel all feels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You could also just go ride a rollercoaster :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope there are no lions chasing you this week, real or imaginary. But if there are, smack those bastards down. I’m rooting for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All my love&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sam&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Sam Beckbessinger</name><email>howzit@fuckinggrownups.com</email></author><category term="psychology" /><category term="mental health" /><category term="stress" /><summary type="html">Three days after my dad died, two of my best friends took me to Gold Reef City to ride rollercoasters.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Being kinder to old you 🧓🏻👵🏾👴🏿👵🏼</title><link href="likeafuckinggrownup.com/freedom/being-kinder-to-older-you.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Being kinder to old you 🧓🏻👵🏾👴🏿👵🏼" /><published>2019-04-03T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-04-03T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>likeafuckinggrownup.com/freedom/being-kinder-to-older-you</id><content type="html" xml:base="likeafuckinggrownup.com/freedom/being-kinder-to-older-you.html">&lt;p&gt;Wanna see something hilarious? This is what I’m going to look like when I’m old, according to one EXTREMELY DODGY APP called FaceApp (more on this later).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/oldme-one.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Young Sam&quot; title=&quot;Young Sam&quot; style=&quot;max-width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/oldme-two.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Old Sam&quot; title=&quot;Old Sam&quot; style=&quot;max-width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Guys, I have many feelings about this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Holy shit, that looks exactly like my grandmother.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;CYUUUUUUTE!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;… and also kind of like my mom?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;WEEEEEEEIRD!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Christ my nose is going to get even bigger when I age, isn’t it?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The weird thing about the photo on the right, is that I don’t feel like it’s me. Not really. I feel a lot of warmth towards her, like I would for any other elderly stranger (I love hanging out with old people, they tend to share my affection for apricot jam and daytime soapies). But she’s not me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course, this is why saving for your retirement is so freaking hard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saving money for future you can feel like giving it away to a stranger. The future is a dark valley of unknowns - I have no idea who Older Me is, what she’s into, where she lives or what she wants. So trying to plan my life around HER needs feels really hard. Especially when I have so many needs of my own already.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s science that backs this up. &lt;a href=&quot;https://hbr.org/2013/06/you-make-better-decisions-if-you-see-your-senior-self&quot;&gt;A team of researchers from Stanford&lt;/a&gt; once did a ran fMRI scans on people and found that the brain patterns when people describe themselves 10 years in the future are more similar to when they describe actors than when they describe their current selves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then they got people to put on virtual reality goggles and look at themselves in a mirror. Half of the subjects saw themselves. The other half saw an aged version of themselves. Then they were asked to allocate $1,000 among four options: buying something nice for someone special, investing in a retirement fund, planning a fun event, or putting money into a spending account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The people who saw the aged image saved nearly twice as much for retirement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The math on saving for retirement isn’t that hard. A basic rule of thumb is to take half your age that you start saving for retirement, and save that percentage of your income (so save 15% if you start at 30, save 25% if you start at 50). Or you can get more hardcore than that and read up about the 4% rule (your savings target is 25 x your annual expenses). Pretty much every country offers tax-efficient options for those savings. There are dozens of articles about all of this online (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stealthywealth.co.za/2018/01/the-best-ra-in-south-africa.html&quot;&gt;South Africans, here’s a good one for you&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But like so much else, the hard part about money &lt;strong&gt;isn’t the money part&lt;/strong&gt;. The hard part is confronting your own emotions. The hard part is dealing with the fact that one day - if you’re lucky - you are going to be old. One day you’ll probably not be able to work any more. One day you will be a different person to the person you are now. And that person is your child, in a way, in that they are 100% dependent on you and your choices now. You are responsible for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have to remind yourself of this. Because we tend to forget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Buddhists have been onto this for centuries. In some countries, they do a practice called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mara%E1%B9%87asati&quot;&gt;corpse meditation&lt;/a&gt;, where they sit for hours and contemplate photographs of dead bodies in various stages of composition. Sometimes, they do this with real corpses that are donated to the temples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This might seem morbid as heck. But maybe it’s healthier than what the Western World does, which is hide away death and ageing and refuse to ever discuss it in the cultural equivalent to sticking our fingers in our ears and going LA LA LA LA I’M NEVER GOING TO DIE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way I try to combat this is to make sure that I have some heroes who are old, and not let the media full my mind only with aspirational 20 year old pop stars with perfect bodies. I try to have models for what being old can look like, and how rad it can be. I think about women like Patti Smith, bell smith, Margaret Atwood, Laurie Anderson - how they’re still making subversive and important work in their 60s and 70s. How they seem to give fewer and fewer fucks as they age. Or my #1 old woman idol: the late, great Eartha Kitt who was cool as hell until the day she slipped off this earth to get into something more comfortable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will make different choices for your life if you spend time thinking about your own Old Self. They might still feel like a different person, but at least you could become better acquainted with them. Even start to feel compassion for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m working on my dreams for Old Me. I want her to be one of those old women who wears neon muumuus all the time and does oil paintings of weirdly sexual fruits and has orange hair and fourteen cats and says rude things all the time because she gives no fucks. I want her to go on archeology tours and take psychedelics and get a pointless PhD and hike in the mountains by herself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, to give Old Me the chance to do those things, &lt;strong&gt;here are four big things I’m doing at the moment:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Trying to build up a running habit, because she’s going to need this heart to keep pumping for several more decades, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/the-top-10-causes-of-death&quot;&gt;heart disease is the way Old Me is most likely to die&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Keep putting work into my friendships, and not letting one person be my only source of support. Relationships are what give life meaning, and you have to diversify because no-one lives forever.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Building a career that gives my life meaning and doesn’t rely on someone else employing me, because people are dicks about employing old people.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Saving as much freaking money for her as I can.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What do you want for Old You?&lt;/strong&gt; And what are you going to do now, to give them a better chance at having that life? Tell me in an email - I will read it! I’ll share some of my favourite answers with the rest of you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All my love&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Younger Sam (borrowing the body that will one day belong to Old Sam).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Psst… guys, as fun as they are, be careful using apps that put cool filters on your photos. My friend, data privacy activist Murray Hunter, says this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“FaceApp’s built up a database of about 150million people’s faces — which it’s likely using to train facial-recognition algorithms.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;“It’s a symptom of a much bigger problem, given the myriad ways that facial recognition is being rolled out across the world. A lot of people talk about this as the users’ fault but we need to put the blame squarely with the companies and governments and crappy laws that enable these practices.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Murray is crowdfunding a hilarious children’s book to help you have better conversations about data privacy with toddlers (I’ve read it; it’s mega cute). &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.indiegogo.com/projects/boris-the-babybot-a-storybook-about-surveillance/x/22185084?utm_source=sailthru&amp;amp;utm_medium=email&amp;amp;utm_campaign=bck-07292019update&amp;amp;utm_term=#/&quot;&gt;Pre-order yours here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Sam Beckbessinger</name><email>howzit@fuckinggrownups.com</email></author><category term="retirement" /><category term="money" /><category term="psychology" /><summary type="html">Wanna see something hilarious? This is what I’m going to look like when I’m old, according to one EXTREMELY DODGY APP called FaceApp (more on this later).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What might you earn over the rest of your lifetime?</title><link href="likeafuckinggrownup.com/freedom/lifetime-earnings.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What might you earn over the rest of your lifetime?" /><published>2019-01-28T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-01-28T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>likeafuckinggrownup.com/freedom/lifetime-earnings</id><content type="html" xml:base="likeafuckinggrownup.com/freedom/lifetime-earnings.html">&lt;p&gt;Visualise all the money you’re still going to earn over the rest of your life. Close your eyes and picture it for a moment, a big pile of cash, like something Scrooge McDuck might go swimming in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can you see it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine picking up one or two of those pieces of paper. Each bit of cash is a piece of possibility. You could do anything with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have you ever stopped to think about how big that pile might actually be?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s an estimate for you, based on your age and your monthly income:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/lifetime-earnings.png&quot; alt=&quot;Lifetime earnings table&quot; title=&quot;Lifetime earnings table&quot; style=&quot;max-width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Holy shitballs, that’s a big number, right? How much of that money are you going to spend on the stuff that really matters to you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;howd-i-work-out-that-number&quot;&gt;How’d I work out that number?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, I use this formula:
Lifetime earnings = (current salary x 12) x ((((1.06) ^ (65 - current age)) - 1) / 0.06)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Sam Beckbessinger</name><email>howzit@fuckinggrownups.com</email></author><category term="freedom" /><category term="earning" /><category term="making money" /><summary type="html">Visualise all the money you’re still going to earn over the rest of your life. Close your eyes and picture it for a moment, a big pile of cash, like something Scrooge McDuck might go swimming in.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How well do you know your partner’s money style?</title><link href="likeafuckinggrownup.com/etc/money-questions.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How well do you know your partner's money style?" /><published>2018-05-12T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-05-12T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>likeafuckinggrownup.com/etc/money-questions</id><content type="html" xml:base="likeafuckinggrownup.com/etc/money-questions.html">&lt;p&gt;It might sound unromantic, but learning how to talk about money in your relationship is one of the most important things you can do to keep your love alive, because money problems are one of the most common reasons for divorce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Money touches all of our fears, our insecurities, our hopes and our values. So here’s an exercise to help you get onto the same page: a list of money questions for you and your partner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Put aside an evening, make your favourite dinner, and spend some time independently writing down your answers to these questions. When you’re done, swop answers and read what your partner wrote. These questions will ask you to think about your financial goals, beliefs and worries, and learn about theirs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depending on where you are in your relationship, you might want to skip some of these questions. Agree which ones you want to answer before you begin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s important to go into this exercise with love, patience and empathy for each other. Remember, this exercise is mostly about &lt;strong&gt;learning about your partner&lt;/strong&gt;, not just convincing them of your point of view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-questions&quot;&gt;The Questions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;your-money-type&quot;&gt;Your money type&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What emotions come up for you when we talk about money?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What’s more important to you: security, or experiences?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Are you a spender or a saver?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What did you like about how your family handled money growing up?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What didn’t you like?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What worries you most about your partner’s financial behaviour?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What are the ways you think your partner is better with money than you are?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What worries you most about your own financial behaviour?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;your-money-situation&quot;&gt;Your money situation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How much do you earn?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How much debt do you have?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How much do you have in savings and investments?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What are some big financial goals you have for the next 5 years?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What about for the next 30?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What steps are you taking to reach your financial goals? What steps would you like to take?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What’s the worst money mistake you made in the past?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;budgeting-and-money-management&quot;&gt;Budgeting and money management&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do you like to have a detailed budget?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do you save at the beginning or end of the month?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do you think it’s important that couples share all their money in a single account? Why?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do you think it’s important that couples have some private spending money? Why?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What is the maximum we could spend independently without consulting each other?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What are the indulgent expenses that give you the most happy?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What are the things in our household budget that you think we should cut back on?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Who should be in charge of investing for our future?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;money-values&quot;&gt;Money values&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do you think debt is bad?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If there came a time where one of us earned much more than the other, what would be the fair way to split the bills?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How much do you think holidays should cost?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How much do you think we should have in savings for emergencies?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do you hope to start a business, study further, or take a long sabbatical one day? How would we fund this?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;kids-and-family&quot;&gt;Kids and family&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do you want our (future or current) children to go to a private school? Do you want to be able to pay for tertiary education?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If we had children, how would we split the costs of childcare?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If either of our parents became sick or couldn’t look after themselves any more, how much would we support them?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Would you help your siblings or extended family financially if they needed it? To what limit?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;closing&quot;&gt;Closing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What’s one thing that really excites you when you think about your future together with your partner?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/love.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Love&quot; title=&quot;Love&quot; style=&quot;max-width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Sam Beckbessinger</name><email>howzit@fuckinggrownups.com</email></author><category term="tools" /><category term="etc" /><category term="downloads" /><summary type="html">It might sound unromantic, but learning how to talk about money in your relationship is one of the most important things you can do to keep your love alive, because money problems are one of the most common reasons for divorce.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The all-in-one flowchart for managing your money</title><link href="likeafuckinggrownup.com/etc/flowchart.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The all-in-one flowchart for managing your money" /><published>2018-03-27T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-03-27T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>likeafuckinggrownup.com/etc/flowchart</id><content type="html" xml:base="likeafuckinggrownup.com/etc/flowchart.html">&lt;p&gt;Feeling overwhelmed about all the different things you need to do in order to get your money life under control? Here’s a simple flowchart that takes you through, step-by-step, all the major milestones you’ll reach on the rocky road to financial freedom.
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ManageYourMoneyLikeAFuckingGrownup-theflowchart.png&quot; alt=&quot;Manage Your Money Like a F*cking Grownup - the flowchart&quot; title=&quot;Manage Your Money Like a F*cking Grownup - the flowchart&quot; style=&quot;max-width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, real life is never simple or linear, so don’t expect your life to track these steps perfectly, either! Think of it like a map: it’s really helpful to have a rough idea of where to go, but the really interesting stuff happens in the little unplanned detours you might take along the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This flowchart is yours to download, print and share as you wish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/downloads/ManageYourMoneyLikeAFuckingGrownup-theflowchart.png&quot; download=&quot;&quot;&gt;Download a high-res version here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Sam Beckbessinger</name><email>howzit@fuckinggrownups.com</email></author><category term="tools" /><category term="get your shit together" /><category term="downloads" /><summary type="html">Feeling overwhelmed about all the different things you need to do in order to get your money life under control? Here’s a simple flowchart that takes you through, step-by-step, all the major milestones you’ll reach on the rocky road to financial freedom.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">GAH! An error in the book</title><link href="likeafuckinggrownup.com/etc/graph-correction.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="GAH! An error in the book" /><published>2018-02-14T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-02-14T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>likeafuckinggrownup.com/etc/graph-correction</id><content type="html" xml:base="likeafuckinggrownup.com/etc/graph-correction.html">&lt;p&gt;Shock! Horror! There’s a tiny mistake in the OTHERWISE 100% PERFECT book!
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On page 77, you’ll find this graph comparing the impact on your net worth of taking R1000 out of savings vs. taking a loan for it. I’m a moron and I switched the key around. The RED bars show you what happens if you pull the money out of savings, and the BLACK bars show you what happens if you take a loan for the money. The X-axis compares how long you take to pay back the money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/graph-pg-77.png&quot; alt=&quot;Page 77 graph&quot; title=&quot;Page 77 graph&quot; style=&quot;max-width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Woops. Sorry.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Sam Beckbessinger</name><email>howzit@fuckinggrownups.com</email></author><category term="etc" /><category term="book" /><summary type="html">Shock! Horror! There’s a tiny mistake in the OTHERWISE 100% PERFECT book!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Schemes and Scams</title><link href="likeafuckinggrownup.com/freedom/schemes-and-scams.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Schemes and Scams" /><published>2018-02-06T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-02-06T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>likeafuckinggrownup.com/freedom/schemes-and-scams</id><content type="html" xml:base="likeafuckinggrownup.com/freedom/schemes-and-scams.html">&lt;p&gt;There’s no way to get rich quick, but there are a hundred ways for people to lose everything because they try to. Here’s our list of money making schemes and scams that we think you should avoid, because we don’t want you to lose your hard-earned moolah.
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will not link to any of these sites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;under-investigation&quot;&gt;Under investigation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These schemes are being investigated by the South African National Consumer Commission, because they might be pyramid schemes. Avoid them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;MMM&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kipi AKA Mydeposit241&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Direct Direct Intervention Program to Empower South Africans (Dipesa)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Instant Wealth Club&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make Believe&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;NMT Investments&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sikhese&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wealth Creation Club&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;WorldVentures&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/MMM.png&quot; alt=&quot;MMM&quot; title=&quot;MMM&quot; style=&quot;max-width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;gross-mlm-businesses&quot;&gt;Gross MLM businesses&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are highly suspect multi-level marketing businesses that are more about you selling the opportunity become a salesperson, than about selling the actual product. These businesses are (probably) not actually illegal, but I want you to stay away from them please because I love you and I don’t want you to lose your friends and money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Clientèle Life&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Amway&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;WorldVentures&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Herbalife&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mannatech&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Avon&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Nu-Skin&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Agel&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bitcoin-and-schemes&quot;&gt;Bitcoin and schemes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bitcoin schemes are all the rage these days. There are so many popping up every day it can be hard to keep track, but here’s a good article about &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bitcoinzar.co.za/bitcoin-schemes-south-africa/&quot;&gt;how to identify a Bitcoin scam&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;got-any-tips&quot;&gt;Got any tips?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Know of any other dodgy or suspect schemes or scams? Let us know in the comments and we’ll investigate.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Sam Beckbessinger</name><email>howzit@fuckinggrownups.com</email></author><category term="earning" /><category term="scam" /><summary type="html">There’s no way to get rich quick, but there are a hundred ways for people to lose everything because they try to. Here’s our list of money making schemes and scams that we think you should avoid, because we don’t want you to lose your hard-earned moolah.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Radtastic investment funds and savings accounts</title><link href="likeafuckinggrownup.com/investing/good-funds.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Radtastic investment funds and savings accounts" /><published>2018-02-06T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-02-06T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>likeafuckinggrownup.com/investing/good-funds</id><content type="html" xml:base="likeafuckinggrownup.com/investing/good-funds.html">&lt;p&gt;Guys, there are a lot of different accounts and funds out there, and I’m not listing every single one of them here. These are just some of the funds that I’ve personally scouted out as potential candidates for my own portfolio.
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Heyyyyyyy… remember how I’m not a professional, qualified financial adviser? Just reminding you of that fact. Do your own homework before you put your money in something and &lt;a href=&quot;/etc/get-some-advice.html&quot;&gt;talk to an actual financial adviser&lt;/a&gt; if you need to. Kthnxbai.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Psst: if you do want a pretty comprehensive list of funds in South Africa, try &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fundsdata.co.za/navs/default.htm&quot;&gt;this link.&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I like to choose things that:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Have the &lt;strong&gt;lowest possible costs&lt;/strong&gt; (look for the “total expense ratio” or “total investment cost”) - this almost always means passive index investing. You should read chapter 7 of the book for the full debate on active vs. passive funds and make up your own mind about this.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Are with &lt;strong&gt;reputable, legit companies&lt;/strong&gt; that won’t vanish with my money.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Are friendly for people who like to &lt;strong&gt;handle their investments themselves, online&lt;/strong&gt; because, come on, it’s 2019.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, you need to choose the right type of fund, with the right asset allocation, for your time period, which will tell you what your risk appetite should be. The basic rule for this is that the sooner you want to spend that chunk of money, the lower the risk rating you’re looking for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New funds come out all the time! And I’m also not a wizard, so I might have missed some really great options. If you’ve found a fund that you think is hella-mega-cool, let me know about it so that we can keep building this list together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Last updated: 14 October 2019&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/plan.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Find a fund&quot; title=&quot;Find a fund&quot; style=&quot;max-width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;looking-for-a-cheap-bank-account&quot;&gt;Looking for a cheap bank account?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moneyweb ran a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.moneyweb.co.za/news/industry/the-cheapest-bank-account-is-old-mutuals/&quot;&gt;pretty good comparison&lt;/a&gt; of the different bank account options and their pricing. The result? Depending on your banking behaviour, the cheapest bank is either &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.capitecbank.co.za&quot;&gt;Capitec&lt;/a&gt; or (believe it or not) &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.oldmutualfinance.co.za/money-account&quot;&gt;Old Mutual&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New challenger bank &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tymebank.co.za/&quot;&gt;Tymebank&lt;/a&gt; is great, but they have some weird account limits that mean they’re not right for people who are likely to have significant cash coming into their account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Thanks to John Nel for pointing me to this link!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;looking-for-a-savings-account-for-your-emergency-fund-or-table-flip-fund&quot;&gt;Looking for a savings account for your emergency fund or table flip fund?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s hard to compare apples with apples here, because different accounts have different minimum deposits and notice periods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Provider&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Account name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Link&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Max interest rate&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Minimum amount&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Notice period&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Tymebank&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Goalsave&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tymebank.co.za/banking/personal/goal-save/&quot;&gt;Fund link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;R100&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Instant&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;FNB&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Money Maximiser&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fnb.co.za/invest/money-maximiser.html&quot;&gt;Fund link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;6.95%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;R100 000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Instant&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;FNB&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;32 Day Flexi Notice&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fnb.co.za/invest/32-day-flexi-notice.html&quot;&gt;Fund link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;6.70%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;R1 000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;32 days&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Bidvest&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Fixed Deposit Call Accounts&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bidvestbank.co.za/personal-banking/banking/banking-for-individuals.aspx&quot;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;6.65%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;R5 000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;41 days&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Absa&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Notice Select 32 Days&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.absa.co.za/personal/save-invest/products/notice-select/&quot;&gt;Fund link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;6.55%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;R1 000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;32 days&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;FNB&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;7 Day Notice&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fnb.co.za/invest/7-day-notice-deposit.html&quot;&gt;Fund link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;6.40%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;R20 000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;7 days&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Absa&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Notice Select 7 Days&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.absa.co.za/personal/save-invest/products/notice-select/&quot;&gt;Fund link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;6.40%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;R1 000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;7 days&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Absa&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Depositor Plus&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.absa.co.za/personal/save-invest/products/depositor-plus/&quot;&gt;Fund link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;6.20%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;R0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Instant&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Standard Bank&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;MoneyMarket Call Account&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.standardbank.co.za/standardbank/Personal/Fees,-rates-%26-prices/Interest-rates/MoneyMarket-Call-Account&quot;&gt;Fund link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;6.00%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;R20 000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Instant&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Capitec&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Flexible Savings Account&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.capitecbank.co.za/global-one/save/rates-and-fees&quot;&gt;Fund link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;5.50%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;R0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Instant&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;FNB&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Money On Call&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fnb.co.za/invest/money-on-call.html&quot;&gt;Fund link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4.90%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;R5 000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Instant&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Absa&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;TruSave&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.absa.co.za/personal/save-invest/products/absa-trusave/&quot;&gt;Fund link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3.45%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;R50&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Instant&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Standard Bank&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;PureSave&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.standardbank.co.za/standardbank/Personal/Fees,-rates-%26-prices/Interest-rates/PureSave&quot;&gt;Fund link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2.60%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;R50&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Instant&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right now, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tymebank.co.za/&quot;&gt;Tymebank&lt;/a&gt; offers the best interest on day-to-day savings, but there’s a limit to the maximum amount of money you can have in your account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t get too excited about those interest rates from Absa and Standard Bank - they have different interest tiers depending on how much money you have saved, and those are the maximums, often requiring you to have a few million in the account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technically that FNB Money Maximiser is a money market fund, but you interact with it like a savings account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investec.com/en_za/savings-accounts/daily-rates.html&quot;&gt;Investec&lt;/a&gt; also has some great rates for savings accounts, but they typically need a minimum balance of R100k.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.oldmutualfinance.co.za/money-account&quot;&gt;Old Mutual Money Account&lt;/a&gt; actually puts your savings in a money market unit trust, which means it’s actually a pretty great option for most people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a pretty cool &lt;a href=&quot;https://mytreasury.co.za/&quot;&gt;online calculator&lt;/a&gt; that will help you find the savings account where you can get the best interest rate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;looking-for-a-money-market-fund-because-your-short-term-savings-have-gotten-huge&quot;&gt;Looking for a money market fund because your short-term savings have gotten huge?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Provider&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Fund name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Link&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;TER&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Minimum amount (monthly)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Annualised return (10 yrs)&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Allan Gray&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Money Market Fund&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.allangray.co.za/fund-pages/money-market-fund/&quot;&gt;Fund link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.29%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;R500&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;7.8%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Sygnia&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Money Market Fund A&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sygnia.co.za/docs/default-source/individuals---fund-fact-sheets/unit-trusts/2019-aug-(symca)-sygnia-money-market-fund-class-a---fund-fact-sheet.pdf?sfvrsn=90&quot;&gt;Fund link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.33%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;R500&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;7.4%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Cadiz&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Money Market Fund&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cadiz.co.za/personal-investment/unit-trusts/cadiz-money-market-fund/&quot;&gt;Fund link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.25%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;R1 000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;7.79%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Coronation&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Money Market Fund&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coronation.com/personal/funds/money-market/#js-overview&quot;&gt;Fund link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.25%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;R10 000 lump sum&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;7.8%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Satrix&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Money Market Fund&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.satrix.co.za/media/20447?inline=true&quot;&gt;Fund link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.29%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;R500&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;7.11%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;looking-for-a-conservative-investment-for-a-special-savings-goal&quot;&gt;Looking for a conservative investment for a special savings goal?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can buy most of these funds directly from the provider’s website, or try &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.easyequities.co.za/&quot;&gt;EasyEquities&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Provider&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Fund name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Link&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;TER&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Nedgroup Investments&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Core Guarded Fund&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nedgroupinvestments.co.za/Funds/FundDetailsPage/nedgroup-investments-core-guarded-fund&quot;&gt;Fund link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.50%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Satrix&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Low Equity Balanced Index&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.satrix.co.za/products/product-details?id=30&amp;amp;TabSelection=Unit%20Trust&quot;&gt;Fund link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.47%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Sygnia&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Skeleton Balanced 40&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sygnia.co.za/docs/default-source/individuals---fund-fact-sheets/unit-trusts/2019-aug-(sbfca)-sygnia-skeleton-balanced-40---ffs_2016_skel.pdf?sfvrsn=96&quot;&gt;Fund link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.49%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Prescient&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Absolute Defensive Fund&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.prescient.co.za/funds/multi-asset-funds/prescient-absolute-defensive-fund/&quot;&gt;Fund link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.76%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Old Mutual&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Core Conservative Fund&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.oldmutual.co.za/docs/default-source/unit-trust/ut08factsheets/OldMutualCoreConservativeFund.pdf&quot;&gt;Fund link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.79%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;FNB&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Stable Fund of Funds&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fnb.co.za/downloads/unittrust/Stable_fund.pdf&quot;&gt;Fund link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.84%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Sygnia&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;CPI + 2% Fund&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sygnia.co.za/docs/default-source/individuals---fund-fact-sheets/unit-trusts/2019-aug-(sgccd)-sygnia-cpi-2-fund---fund-fact-sheet.pdf?sfvrsn=100&quot;&gt;Fund link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1.64%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Sygnia&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;CPI + 4% Fund&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sygnia.co.za/docs/default-source/individuals---fund-fact-sheets/unit-trusts/2019-aug-(syccd)-sygnia-cpi-4-fund---fund-fact-sheet.pdf?sfvrsn=102&quot;&gt;Fund link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1.75%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local financial education site Just One Lap has a &lt;a href=&quot;https://justonelap.com/etf-bundles/&quot;&gt;recommended low-risk ETF portfolio&lt;/a&gt; that’s really good. You have to register to see it, but it’s free!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;looking-for-a-global-index-etf-for-your-freedom-fund&quot;&gt;Looking for a global index ETF for your freedom fund?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best summary of which global ETF you should buy is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stealthywealth.co.za/2019/04/war-of-worlds.html&quot;&gt;from Stealthy Wealth&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.easyequities.co.za/&quot;&gt;EasyEquities&lt;/a&gt; is a very easy place to buy most of these funds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;RAND-DENOMINATED FUNDS:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Provider&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Fund name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Link&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;TER&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Currency&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Satrix&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;MSCI World&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.satrix.co.za/products/product-details?id=33&amp;amp;TabSelection=ETF&quot;&gt;Fund link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.35%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;SA Rands&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Stanlib&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;MSCI World Index Feeder ETF&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://indexinvestments.stanlib.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/09/STANLIB-MSCI-World-Index-Feeder-ETF-1.pdf&quot;&gt;Fund link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.4%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;SA Rands&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Ashburton&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Global 1200 Equity ETF&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ashburtoninvestments.com/za/individual-investor/fund/ashburton-global-1200-etf/zae00249967&quot;&gt;Fund link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.67%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;SA Rands&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Sygnia&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Itrix MSCI World&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sygnia.co.za/etfs/fund-details/fund/msci-world-index-etf&quot;&gt;Fund link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.68%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;SA Rands&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;U.S.-DENOMINATED FUNDS:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Fund name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Link&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;TER&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Currency&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Vanguard S&amp;amp;P 500&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://personal.vanguard.com/us/funds/snapshot?FundIntExt=INT&amp;amp;FundId=0968&amp;amp;funds_disable_redirect=true&quot;&gt;Fund link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.03%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;US Dollars&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;iShares S&amp;amp;P 500 ETF&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ishares.com/us/products/239726/ishares-core-sp-500-etf&quot;&gt;Fund link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.04%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;US Dollars&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;iShares MSCI Total International Stock&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ishares.com/us/products/244048/ishares-core-msci-total-international-stock-etf&quot;&gt;Fund link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.09%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;US Dollars&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Vanguard Total World Stock&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://personal.vanguard.com/pub/Pdf/sp3141.pdf?2210111870&quot;&gt;Fund link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.09%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;US Dollars&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Vanguard Russell 3000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://personal.vanguard.com/us/funds/snapshot?FundId=3354&amp;amp;FundIntExt=INT&amp;amp;funds_disable_redirect=true&quot;&gt;Fund link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.15%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;US Dollars&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;iShares MSCI World ETF&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ishares.com/us/literature/fact-sheet/urth-ishares-msci-world-etf-fund-fact-sheet-en-us.pdf&quot;&gt;Fund link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.24%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;US Dollars&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The US Dollar accounts are ones that you can open locally, online, as a South African, but you need to use US Dollars to invest in them. This means making an international transfer from your online banking profile or buying US Dollars in an app like &lt;a href=&quot;https://getshyft.co.za/&quot;&gt;Shyft&lt;/a&gt;. This does mean that you’ll need to take currency conversion costs into account, when comparing your options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Local financial education site Just One Lap has a &lt;a href=&quot;https://justonelap.com/etf-bundles/&quot;&gt;recommended high-risk ETF portfolio&lt;/a&gt; that’s really good. You have to register to see it, but it’s free!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;looking-for-a-retirement-annuity-so-that-youre-not-going-to-be-old-and-poor&quot;&gt;Looking for a retirement annuity so that you’re not going to be old and poor?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of these funds are Regulation 28 compliant, which means that you get the sweet, sweet tax breaks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once again, our good friend &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stealthywealth.co.za/2018/01/the-best-ra-in-south-africa.html&quot;&gt;Stealthy Wealth&lt;/a&gt; has an excellent comparison for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Provider&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Fund name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Link&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;TER&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Nedgroup&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Core Diversified&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nedgroupinvestments.co.za/Funds/FundDetailsPage/nedgroup-investments-core-diversified-fund&quot;&gt;Fund link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.58%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Sygnia&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Skeleton Balanced 70&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sygnia.co.za/docs/default-source/individuals---fund-fact-sheets/unit-trusts/2019-aug-(ssbca)-sygnia-skeleton-balanced-70---ffs_2016_skel.pdf?sfvrsn=102&quot;&gt;Fund link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.76%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Satrix&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Balanced Index Fund&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://satrix.co.za/media/20442?inline=true&quot;&gt;Fund link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.76%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10X&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Retirement Annuity (High Equity)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.10x.co.za/retirement-annuity&quot;&gt;Fund link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1.00%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Coronation&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Balanced Fund Plus&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coronation.com/personal/funds/balanced-plus/&quot;&gt;Fund link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1.60%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Allan Gray&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Balanced Fund&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.allangray.co.za/fund-pages/balanced-fund/&quot;&gt;Fund link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1.70%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just a note on 10X: their fees get a bit lower once you’ve got like R1-million invested with them.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Sam Beckbessinger</name><email>howzit@fuckinggrownups.com</email></author><category term="tools" /><category term="investing" /><category term="freedom" /><category term="accounts" /><summary type="html">Guys, there are a lot of different accounts and funds out there, and I’m not listing every single one of them here. These are just some of the funds that I’ve personally scouted out as potential candidates for my own portfolio.</summary></entry></feed>